<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="dd-guide.xsl"?>
<dataDictionaryKey>
  <att>
    <name>field name</name>
    <defn>The field name is the name of the field (column) in a table.</defn>
  </att>
  <att>
    <name>nulls</name>
    <defn>Whether or not nulls are allowed in this field.</defn>
    <possValue>
      <value>no</value>
      <valueMeaning>Every record (row) in the table must have a value for this field (column), that is none can be blank.</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>yes</value>
      <valueMeaning>Blank fields are allowed in this field (column).
</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
  </att>
  <att>
    <name>key</name>
    <defn>Key shows whether or not the field is a primary key (PK), foreign key (FK), or neither (n/a).</defn>
    <possValue>
      <value>PK</value>
      <valueMeaning>The field is a Primary Key, which is a unique numeric identifier that identifies only one record in a particular table.</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>FK</value>
      <valueMeaning>The field is a Foreign Key, which points to (references) a primary key in another table to link the data in that table's particular record to the data in this table for this record.  For example, a foreign key in the SoilObs table, Observation_ID, points to a record in the observation table identified by the Observation_ID field in the observation table.</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>n/a</value>
      <valueMeaning>The field is neither a primary key nor a foreign key.  The field simply contains data of some kind, but does not reference or identify other data specifically.</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
  </att>
  <att>
    <name>type</name>
    <defn>The data type of the field in question.  All data in this field must fit the rules for the data type.  For example, letters are not allowed in a numeric field.</defn>
    <possValue>
      <value>Boolean</value>
      <valueMeaning>True or False</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>Date</value>
      <valueMeaning>a date-time</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>Float</value>
      <valueMeaning>a number that may contain digits after the decimal point</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>BLOB</value>
      <valueMeaning>Binary Large OBject- contains binary data, such as images</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>Integer</value>
      <valueMeaning>long integer, -2147483648 to +2147483647</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>serial</value>
      <valueMeaning>integer, 0 to +2147483647</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>text</value>
      <valueMeaning>variable length character string (no set limit)</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>varchar</value>
      <valueMeaning>variable length character string (limited to specific number of characters)</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
  </att>
  <att>
    <name>references</name>
    <defn>For foreign key fields (FK), the database field to which this field points to (references) in the format: TableName.FieldName
  For fields that are not a foreign key, references is "n/a."</defn>
  </att>
  <att>
    <name>list</name>
    <defn>Some fields in the database supply a list of choices for values that the field may contain.</defn>
    <possValue>
      <value>closed</value>
      <valueMeaning>The field may only contain values that are contained in the current list.  Values may not be added to the list.</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>open</value>
      <valueMeaning>A list of values is provided for convenience and the use of such values is encouraged where they are accurate.  However, no value in the list is appropriate for the field, then a different value may be used, as well.</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
    <possValue>
      <value>no</value>
      <valueMeaning>No list is attached to this field.  Any value of this field's data type are permitted.</valueMeaning>
    </possValue>
  </att>
  <att>
    <name>field notes</name>
    <defn>notes about the field that give some brief information about the field</defn>
  </att>
  <att>
    <name>field definition</name>
    <defn>a full explanation of the data that is stored in this field</defn>
  </att>
</dataDictionaryKey>
