<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE dataModel SYSTEM "tableStructure.dtd">

<dataModel>	
<title>plantTaxa Plant Taxa Name Usage (Table)</title>
<author>J. Harris</author>
<institution>NCEAS</institution>
<contributor>null</contributor>
<description>null</description>
<date>Mon Oct  2 13:53:21 PDT 2000</date>

<entity>
	<entityName>plntTaxa.PLANTTAXANAMEUSAGE</entityName>
	<entitySummary>Stores information linking a party to a name-circumscription relationship.</entitySummary>
	<entityDescription>The nameUsage table is a 3 way intersection between party, name and circumscription, which
	basically tracks how a party applies a circumscription to a name over time.  The acceptence attribute
	is a relatively new addition and is domain locked to the values 'standard' and 'accepted'.  Name_Usage.acceptance refers to acceptance of a name by a party.  Both "A" 
(accepted) and "S" (standard) mean that according to the party, the name 
points to the circumscription indicated. In addition if the value is "S", 
then this is the name that the party assigns to the referenced circumscription.  
At one time in the perspective of a party here can be many names with an 
"A" relative to a single circumscription, but there can be only one "S".

Status.status refers to acceptance of a circumscription by a party. 
The taxonomy of a party at a given time should be devised so that a given
organism can belong to only one standard ("S") circumscription; any others 
that include the organisms must be indicated to be nponstandard ("N"), or 
can be absent from the status table altogether. </entityDescription>
	<attribute> 
		<attName>NAME_USAGE_ID</attName>
		<attNulls>No</attNulls>	
		<attType>NUMBER</attType>
		<attKey>PK</attKey>
		<attNotes>n/a </attNotes>
		<attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
		<attDefinition>Database assigned value corresponding to a unique usage of a name-circumscription usage by a particular party.</attDefinition>
	</attribute>


 <attribute>
                <attName>CIRCUM_ID</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER</attType>
                <attKey>FK</attKey>
                <attReferences>CIRCUMSCRIPTION</attReferences>
                <attNotes>Foreign key into the CIRCUMSCRIPTION table.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This attribute is the key pointing to a specific circumscription.</attDefinition>        </attribute>



 <attribute>
                <attName>NAME_ID</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER</attType>
                <attKey>FK</attKey>
		<attReferences>NAME</attReferences>
                <attNotes>Foreign key into the NAME table.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This attribute is the key pointing to a taxon name.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>



        <attribute>
                <attName>PARTY_ID</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER</attType>
                <attKey>FK</attKey>
                <attReferences>PARTY</attReferences>
                <attNotes>n/a </attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This attribute is the key pointing to a specific party.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>



<attribute>
                <attName>USAGE_STARTDATE</attName>
                <attNulls>Yes</attNulls>
                <attType>DATE</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
		<attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>n/a</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is the date on which a party stated using a specific circumscription.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>



        <attribute>
                <attName>USAGE_STOPDATE</attName>
                <attNulls>Yes</attNulls>
                <attType>DATE</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>n/a </attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is the date on which a party stops using a specific circumscription.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>


	<children> </children>
</entity>
</dataModel>	
