<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE dataModel SYSTEM "tableStructure.dtd">

<dataModel>     
<title>plantTaxa Name (Table)</title>
<author>J. Harris</author>
<institution>NCEAS</institution>
<contributor>null</contributor>
<description>null</description>
<date>Mon Oct  2 13:53:21 PDT 2000</date>

<entity>
	<entityName>plantTaxa.REFERENCE </entityName>
	<entitySummary>Stores reference information about plant names and circumscriptions.</entitySummary>
	<entityDescription>This table stores reference information about names and circumscriptions. </entityDescription>
	<attribute> 
		<attName>REF_ID </attName>
		<attNulls>No </attNulls>	
		<attType>NUMBER </attType>
		<attKey>PK</attKey>
		<attNotes>Internal database value </attNotes>
		<attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
		<attDefinition>Database assigned value corresponding to a unique reference</attDefinition>
	</attribute>



	<attribute>
                <attName>AUTHOR</attName>
                <attNulls>TEXT</attNulls>
                <attType>No</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>In upcomming versions, this attribute will be broken down into salutation, givenname and surname</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is the name of the author of a specific reference which may include an author of a
		reference describing the original use of a taxon name or the author of a reference describing a circumscription. </attDefinition>
        </attribute>

<attribute>
                <attName>DATE_ENTERED</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>DATE</attType>
                <attKey>n/a </attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a </attReferences>
                <attNotes>n/a </attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is the date that a reference was added to the database. </attDefinition>
        </attribute>
<attribute>
                <attName>CITATION</attName>
                <attNulls>Yes</attNulls>
                <attType>TEXT</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>In later versions, this attribute will be broken into multiple attributes such as title, publication date, edition, etc.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is information corresponding to a specific citation which may be either a circumscription or an entry 
		for the first time description for a given plant taxon.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>
<attribute>
                <attName>PAGE</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>TEXT</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>This attribute stores either the page number on which the the reference occurs.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>n/a </attDefinition>
        </attribute>
<attribute>
                <attName>REFERENCETYPE</attName>
                <attNulls>Yes</attNulls>
                <attType>TEXT</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>This value will become obsolete in future versions of the data model because it can be infered from other entities.  It was included for database quality checking.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This atrribute can include values: circumscription or origName only.  References of type circumscription mean the 
		the reference defines a circumsrcription wheras those references defined as origname refer to a reference used to describe the original
		ues or a taxon name.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>

<attribute>
                <attName>SPECIESNAME</attName>
                <attNulls>Yes</attNulls>
                <attType>TEXT</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>This attribute stores either the taxon name used in the reference.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition> </attDefinition>
</attribute>
	
	
	<children> </children>
</entity>
</dataModel>	
