<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE dataModel SYSTEM "tableStructure.dtd">

<dataModel>	
<title> Prototype Veg Plots Database Component Description: TaxonObservation </title>
<author>J. Harris </author>
<institution>NCEAS </institution>
<contributor> </contributor>
<description> </description>
<date></date>




<entity>
	<entityName>vegPlot.TAXONOBSERVATION </entityName>
	<entitySummary>This table stores information about cummulative coverage (coverage accross all strata) of all the taxon recognized within a plot observation.</entitySummary>
	<entityDescription>At the working group meeting at NCEAS in September 2000, it was recognized that this table would store the cummulative coverages of the taxa recognized by the author of the plot.  Also recognized was the importance of maintaining an entity for interpretations of the originak taxa recognized by the plot author, and therefore the entity interpretation was added.</entityDescription>


<attribute>
                <attName>TAXONOBSERVATION_ID</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER</attType>
                <attKey>PK</attKey>
		<attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>Primary key of the table.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>Database assigned value for a unique taxa within a given plot observation.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>


	<attribute> 
		<attName>OBS_ID</attName>
		<attNulls>No</attNulls>	
		<attType>NUMBER</attType>
		<attKey>FK</attKey>
		<attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
		<attNotes>Foreign key into the plotObservation table.</attNotes>
		<attDefinition>Database assigned value for a unique plot observation.</attDefinition>
	</attribute>



	<attribute>
                <attName>authorNameId</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>VARCHAR2</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>original taxon name used by the plot author</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is the taxon name that the author of the plot used to refer to a plant observed within the plot.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>


 <attribute>
                <attName>originalAuthority</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>VARCHAR2</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
		<attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>The authority coupled with the original taxon name
                              from that authority is all that is needed to define a
                              taxon.  This is like Berendsohn's potential
                              species concept.  Both the originalTaxonName and the
                              authority might best viewed as foreign keys to tables in
                              the plants database.
		</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is the authority for the taxon that was used by the plot 
		author to describe a population.  If the originalAuthority is unknown then the 
		author if the plot is the originalAuthority</attDefinition>
        </attribute>



        <attribute>
                <attName>cumStrataCoverage</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>This is NOT a summation of cover in each stratum, but rather total coverage in the plot.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>Percent coverage of a species in all recorded strata combined. </attDefinition>
        </attribute>

	<attribute>
                <attName>inferenceArea</attName>
                <attNulls>Yes</attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>The are used to infer the coverage of the taxon, if not the same as the plot area.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is the measured/predicted area for the space used to infer the 
		coverage of a given taxon.  Generally this should be equal to the plot area but it was 
		recognized that, at times, this area may be larger or smaller than the plot area.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>
	
	<children> </children>
</entity>
</dataModel>	
