<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE dataModel SYSTEM "tableStructure.dtd">

<dataModel>	
<title> Prototype Veg Plots Database Component Description: stratumComposition</title>
<author>J. Harris </author>
<institution>NCEAS </institution>
<contributor> </contributor>
<description> </description>
<date></date>


<entity>
	<entityName>vegPlot.STRATUMCOMPOSITION </entityName>
	<entitySummary>This table stores information about the coverage of a single taxon within a specific stratum.</entitySummary>
	<entityDescription>Recognizing that a given taxon may exist within multiople strata, this entity was included as an intersection between the taxonObservation and strata tables to provide a location of lateral percent coverage of a given taxon within a specific stratum.</entityDescription>
	

	<attribute>
                <attName>STRATUMCOMPOSITION_ID</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER</attType>
                <attKey>PK</attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>n/a</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>Database assigned value for a unique existence of a given taxon within a strata defined to be within a plot.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>



	<attribute> 
		<attName>TAXONOBSERVATION_ID</attName>
		<attNulls>No</attNulls>	
		<attType>NUMBER</attType>
		<attKey>FK</attKey>
		<attReferences>taxonObservation</attReferences>
		<attNotes>Foreign key into the taxonObservation table that points to a specific taxon recognized within the plot observation.</attNotes>
		<attDefinition>Database assigned value for a given taxon within a plot observation.</attDefinition>
	</attribute>



	<attribute>
                <attName>STRATA_ID</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER</attType>
                <attKey>FK</attKey>
                <attReferences>STRATA</attReferences>
                <attNotes>Foreign key into the STRATA table.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>Name of the stratum in which the species occurs.  
		Because a single species may occur in more than one stratum this 
		attribute has a many to one relationship with a single species.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>


<attribute> 
                <attName>percentCoverage</attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER</attType>
                <attKey>n/a</attKey>
		<attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>Because workers use various coverage classification schemes, 
		there will have to either be a 'metadata table' or 'normalization 
		alogrithm' in order to relate percent coverage's using the various 
		classification schemes.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition> Percent coverage of a given species within the given stratum.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>


	<children> </children>
</entity>
</dataModel>	
