<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE dataModel SYSTEM "tableStructure.dtd">

<dataModel>	


<title> Prototype Veg Plots Database Component Description: notationIntersection </title>
<author>J. Harris </author>
<institution>NCEAS </institution>
<contributor> </contributor>
<description>This table stores information linking a notation to a specific attribute associated with a plot.</description>
<date></date>

<entity>
	<entityName>vegPlot.notationIntersection </entityName>
	<entitySummary>This table stores the email addresses of the various parties involved in the collection of plots. </entitySummary>
	<entityDescription>This table was developed with the goal of keeping all the notes associated with 
	the plots in a sigle table rather than disseminated thoughout the database.  Generally this table will point a note to a 
	plot record and specifically to a discreet attribute associated with that plot.</entityDescription>

        <attribute>
                <attName>notationIntersectionId</attName>
                <attNulls>No </attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER </attType>
                <attKey>PK </attKey>
		<attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
                <attNotes>Primary Key </attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is the primary key for the notationIntersection table.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>


	<attribute> 
		<attName>obsId</attName>
		<attNulls>No</attNulls>	
		<attType>NUMBER</attType>
		<attKey>FK </attKey>
		<attReferences>plotObservation</attReferences>
		<attNotes>Foreign key into the plotObservation table.</attNotes>
		<attDefinition>This key links a note with a plotObservation. </attDefinition>
	</attribute>



	<attribute>
                <attName>tableName</attName>
                <attNulls>Yes</attNulls>
                <attType>VARCHAR2 </attType>
                <attKey>n/a </attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a </attReferences>
                <attNotes>Name of the table that the note should be associated with.</attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This column stores the name of the table that the note is associated with.  
		In the case where the note is to be generally applied to the entire observation the string stored 
		here will be "plotObservation" which denotes the broad application of the notation to the entire 
		plot observation.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>

	
	<attribute> 
		<attName>attributeName</attName>
		<attNulls>Yes</attNulls>	
		<attType>VARCHAR2</attType>
		<attKey>n/a</attKey>
		<attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
		<attNotes>Name of the attribute in the table (stored in tableName) that the notation is associated with.</attNotes>
		<attDefinition>This column stores the name of the attribute in the table (stored in tableName) 
		that the notation is associated with.  Business rules maintain that if the tableName equals 'plotObservation' then 
		then this field must be null.</attDefinition>
	</attribute>
	
	
	
	<attribute> 
		<attName>tableRecord</attName>
		<attNulls>Yes</attNulls>	
		<attType>NUMBER</attType>
		<attKey>n/a</attKey>
		<attReferences>n/a</attReferences>
		<attNotes>Record number of the row where the attribute (stored in the "attributeName" column) is located.</attNotes>
		<attDefinition>This column stores the record number (which translates to the primary key value for the table 
		where the 'attributeName' is stored) for the row containing the attribute which the note is associated with.</attDefinition>
	</attribute>
	
	
	
	<attribute> 
		<attName>notationId</attName>
		<attNulls>No</attNulls>	
		<attType>NUMBER</attType>
		<attKey>FK</attKey>
		<attReferences>notation</attReferences>
		<attNotes>Foreign key into the notation table.</attNotes>
		<attDefinition>This key points to a specific notation entry.</attDefinition>
	</attribute>

	<children> </children>
</entity>
</dataModel>	
