<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE dataModel SYSTEM "tableStructure.dtd">

<dataModel>	
<title> Prototype Veg Plots Database Component Description: communityType </title>
<author>J. Harris </author>
<institution>NCEAS </institution>
<contributor> </contributor>
<description> </description>
<date></date>



<entity>
	<entityName>vegPlot.COMMUNITYTYPE </entityName>
	<entitySummary>This table stores the information responsible for the relationship between a plot observation and a community type. </entitySummary>
	<entityDescription>There is still some debate whether or not this entity actually belongs here.  
	The issues here are the same as those surrounding the plant taxa database.  Do we store all the 
	plant taxa, or in this case all the community types, in a database local to the plots datbase or is 
	there a communication process between the plots database and HDMS.  With the plant taxa, we are leaning towards
	developing our own database component to store information related to plant taxa which will be structurally
	similar to that same functional component in HDMS and will at some point probably be updated from HDMS.  
	Fortunately, the designers at TNC have been concerned with designing a 'universal' data model which will
	be capable of storing/tracking either plant taxa or community types or both. </entityDescription>


<attribute>
                <attName>communityType_id </attName>
                <attNulls>No</attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER</attType>
                <attKey>PK </attKey>
		<attReferences> n/a </attReferences>
                <attNotes>The Primary key of the communityType table. </attNotes>
                <attDefinition>Database assigned value for a unique community type applied to a single plot observation. </attDefinition>
        </attribute>



        <attribute>
                <attName>OBS_ID </attName>
                <attNulls>N </attNulls>
                <attType>NUMBER </attType>
                <attKey>FK </attKey>
                <attReferences>plotObservation </attReferences>
                <attNotes>Foreign key into the plotObservation table. </attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This key provides a link between comminity type(s) with a specific plot observation. </attDefinition>
        </attribute>
<attribute>
                <attName>classAssociation </attName>
                <attNulls>No </attNulls>
                <attType>VARCHAR2 </attType>
                <attKey>n/a </attKey>
		<attReferences> n/a </attReferences>
                <attNotes>n/a </attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is the class_association from the National Vegetaion Classification Standard. </attDefinition>
        </attribute>



        <attribute>
                <attName>classificationQuality</attName>
                <attNulls>Yes </attNulls>
                <attType>VARCHAR2 </attType>
                <attKey>n/a </attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a </attReferences>
                <attNotes>This is a very subjective attribute, and may be removed later. </attNotes>
                <attDefinition>This is the quality of the classification assignment. </attDefinition>
        </attribute>




	<attribute> 
		<attName>startDate </attName>
		<attNulls>No </attNulls>	
		<attType>DATE </attType>
		<attKey>n/a </attKey>
		<attReferences> n/a </attReferences>
		<attNotes>n/a </attNotes>
		<attDefinition>Start date for the classification assignment of the plot observation. </attDefinition>
	</attribute>



	<attribute>
                <attName>stopDate </attName>
                <attNulls>No </attNulls>
                <attType>DATE </attType>
                <attKey>n/a </attKey>
                <attReferences>n/a </attReferences>
                <attNotes>n/a </attNotes>
                <attDefinition>Stop date for the classification assignment of the plot observation.</attDefinition>
        </attribute>


	<children> </children>
</entity>
</dataModel>	
